Guide to the Doris Duke Papers, 1798-2003 and undated (bulk 1930-1999)
Duke University. University Archives
Doris Duke Papers 1798-2003 and undated (bulk 1930-1999)
Duke University. University Archives
Duke, Doris, 1912-1993
245 linear feet Extent: 81,656 Items
Born on November 22, 1912, Doris Duke was the only child of James Buchanan (J.B.) Duke, a founder of the American Tobacco Company and Duke Energy Company and a benefactor of Duke University, and Nanaline Holt Duke. Inheriting a bulk of her father's estate in 1925, which included Duke Farms in New Jersey, Rough Point in Newport, R.I., and a mansion in New York City, Doris was soon dubbed by the press as "the richest girl in the world." Although Doris did her best to live a private life, she contributed to a number of public causes and was an active supporter of the arts, historic preservation, and the environment. Doris Duke died in October 1993 at the age of 80. In her will she left the majority of her estate to the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation. The Doris Duke Papers were created by combining materials maintained by staff at the Duke Business Office and/or household staff of the Main Residence, on Doris Duke's behalf. It mostly contains the personal papers generated by or about Doris Duke throughout her lifetime. The collection covers the period 1798 to 2003, although the majority of the collection is concentrated in the 1930s to 1993. The collection is organized into 9 series limited to Doris Duke's personal relationships, dealings, and interests: Administrative Records, Personal Correspondence, Financial Records, Legal Records, Reports and Summaries, Subject Files, and Duke Business Office Safe.
RL.01504
Language: Material in English French Italian
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research, however there are restrictions on certain materials within the collection. See Series level descriptions for more information.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Also, all of this collection is housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Electronic records in this collection have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact a reference archivist before coming to use these records.
Provenance
The Doris Duke Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a donation from the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation in June 2009.
Historical Note
Born on November 22, 1912, Doris Duke was the only child of James Buchanan (J.B.) Duke, a founder of the American Tobacco Company and Duke Energy Company and a benefactor of Duke University, and Nanaline Holt Duke. Inheriting a bulk of her father's estate in 1925, which included Duke Farms in New Jersey, Rough Point in Newport, R.I., and a mansion in New York City, Doris was soon dubbed by the press as "the richest girl in the world." Although Doris did her best to live a private life, she carried on the Duke family's pattern of philanthropy by contributing to a number of public causes such as the arts, historic preservation, and the environment. When she was 21 she established Independent Aid, a foundation which would later became the Doris Duke Foundation. Adventurous, intelligent and independent, Doris Duke was determined not to be defined by social expectations or her vast wealth. She traveled widely and pursued her many interests including music, dance, writing, and art. Doris Duke was married twice, first to James H.R. Cromwell and then to Porfirio Rubirosa. Both marriages ended in divorce. Doris Duke died in October 1993 at the age of 80. In her will she left the majority of her estate to the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation.
Collection Overview
The Doris Duke papers (formerly MSS.001) is part of the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation Historical Archives which were donated to the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library by the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation. The collection is artificial in nature, created by combining materials maintained by staff at the Duke Business Office and/or household staff of the Main Residence, on Doris Duke's behalf. It mostly contains the personal papers generated by or about Doris Duke throughout her lifetime. Since Doris Duke's staff maintained her professional and personal records, often in the same filing structures, materials regarding her personal life were intermingled throughtout the larger collection. In order to improve access to important documents, all materials of a personal nature were selected out and incorporated into this collection. The only major exception is Series VII: Duke Business Office Safe, where the personal and professional contents of the office are maintained together to preserve the integrity of the materials and serve as a testament to business operations.
The Doris Duke Papers covers the period 1798 to 2003, although the majority of the collection is concentrated in the 1930s to 1993. The collection is divided into 7 series limited to Doris Duke's personal relationships, dealings, and interests: Administrative Records, Personal Correspondence (RESTRICTED), Financial Records, Legal Records, Reports and Summaries, Subject Files, and Duke Business Office Safe.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Cromwell, James H. R. (James Henry Roberts), b. 1896.; Duke family; Duke, Doris, 1912-1993; Duke, James Buchanan, 1856-1925; Duke, Nanaline Holt Inman; Rubirosa, Porfirio, 1909-1965; Heiresses; International travel; Philanthropy and society
Related Material
Duke Family Papers, 1885-1992 (bulk 1892-1927)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke Family New York Apartments Collection, 1908-1997
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Doris Duke Papers on the Duke Farms Residence, 1859-2004 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Doris Duke Papers on the Falcon Lair Residence, 1937-1999
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Doris Duke Papers on the Shangri La Residence, 1932-2003
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Doris Duke Papers on the Rough Point Residence, 1922-1997
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Contents of Collection
- Administrative Records, 1906-1993 and undated
  This series contains an assortment of materials related to the broad and varied business and personal activities of Doris Duke. Materials related to business activities include correspondence, agendas, reports, and minutes from Doris Duke's business team. Topics range from investments, new ventures (including the chartering of the Newport Restoration Foundation), and loans, to job descriptions, stock donations, approval of gifts (donations), and information on the General Charitable Aid Association. Other business related materials include activity reports, repairs to homes, design proposals, NRF work progress reports, and requests for interviews. While these materials are related to Doris Duke's business pursuits, the personal side of life is also reflected as the authors often comment on current events and other daily activities such as congratulations on her marriage to Porfirio Rubirosa.
  Materials related to the personal activities of Doris Duke include invitations to a variety of charitable events, solicitations for charitable contributions (letters addressed directly to Doris Duke and not her charitable organization often from individuals not personally acquainted with her), datebooks, address books, personal letters to friends (copies), magazine subscriptions, and correpondence related to travel. Of particular interest is correspondence (letters, telegrams) between Doris Duke and her mother Nanaline and between Doris Duke and her half-brother Walker Inman Sr. (Miss Duke signed her letters "Sis"), and two letters from Doris Duke while on her honeymoon in 1935.
  The materials are loosely arranged in chronological order. Note that the subseries contains several documents written in French and Italian with no translation.
  This series also contains electronic records related to a variety of administrative activities at the Duke Farms residence and includes monthly reports from managers, summaries of correspondence generated by the Duke Business Office staff, telephone messages, and lists of request for donations from the Doris Duke Foundation. The Duke Business Office arranged the electronic records in folders by both subject and by month and year.
  RESTRICTED: Access to several folders in Box 6 are restricted and require prior written approval from the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation to view.
  Electronic records have been migrated to a library server for preservation and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.
  - Meeting agendas and minutes of Doris Duke's meetings with her business team including Mr. Eaton, Mr. Kent, and Mr. Fach, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Business card, Bahram Panahi, First Secretary to the Imperial Embassy of Iran in Washington, D.C., undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Business cards, Antique dealers, circa 1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Catalogs, clothing and orders/cancellations for Doris Duke, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and memoranda related to employees' authority to sign checks, 1973-1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Housekeeping documents related to insurance policies, credit cards, and personal information, 1989-1993 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Insurance-related materials on Doris Duke's rug collection, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Invitations extended to Doris Duke, 1983-1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Invitations, regrets by Doris Duke, 1987-1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Invitations to various fundraising events, including plays and lectures, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Invitations, accepted by Doris Duke, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - List of all employees at Shangri La, Rough Point, Duke Farms, Duke Gardens Foundation, and the Newport Restoration Foundation, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - List of china and towel distribution among homes, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Magazine subscriptions for Doris Duke, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Telephone messages for Doris Duke, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Faxes received at DBO, Duke Farms, involving a variety of administrative activities, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Memoranda containing Doris Duke's daily file of messages, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Faxes sent from DBO to other estates and to Doris Duke with phone messages, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Faxes sent to Doris Duke, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Information on self-help seminars, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Printed materials, tour company information, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Proposal for Nature Center at Duke Island Park, Somerset County Park Commission by Kinsey-Loede Associates, planning associates, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Purchasing information for wine, 1992–1994 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence relating to freight shipments arranged by Thos. Cook & Son, 1935-1937 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence relating to freight shipments arranged by Thos. Cook & Son, 1937-1953 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence and related materials concerning the removal of apartment furnishings from Doris Duke's Paris flat, including piano, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - U.S. Customs forms and Grace International correspondence relating to shipments of Doris Duke's clothing to U.S., 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Materials relating to shipments by air freight and charters by Doris Duke, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Solicitations for charitable contributions, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Sample letterhead and envelope belong to "Doris Duke, Duke Farms Somerville, New Jersey 08876", undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Directions to manufacture wheat starch paste used by the Conservation Center of the Institute of Fine Arts, N.Y.U., 1976 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Alterations and repairs made under Plan No. 48, New Jersey Multiple Unit Laying House at the State College of Agriculture, Rutgers University, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence relating to Edwardo Tirella accident, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Memoranda relating to airline mileage for Miss Duke and Miss Heffner, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Memoranda and other notes relating to purchases made for Doris Duke at Bergdorf Goodman, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to the cleaning and repair of all books at Duke Farms, Shangri La, and Falcon Lair. Includes photocopy of inventory of books (1965). Includes some invoices for book purchases, 1906, 1937-1985 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence relating to Doris Duke's donation of books to the placed aboard the SS James B. Duke operated by Wessel, Duval & Co. Inc. Includes correspondence regarding the christening of the ship, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence relating to John P. Brown's insistence that Doris Duke or NRF owes him money, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Access restricted
  - Memoranda relating to legal files retrieval from Carb Luria, et al. law firm, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Memoranda relating to Doris Duke's catalogue subscriptions from Sotheby's and other administrative matters, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Memoranda and related materials concerning phone messages left by Dr. Deepak Chopra, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence with Chemical Bank about disputed credits reported to Doris Duke's card, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and related materials concerning Doris Duke's donation of $493,000 to the Somerset County Park Commission to improve Duke Island Park (1964). Materials discuss headgates reconstruction project of canal, 1963-1975 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence and brochure relating to Robert Farrah's services to the Near East Dance Foundation and Doris Duke, 1974-1977 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Memoranda and related materials on publications for establishing foundations, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence regarding Hagop Kevorkian Center for Near Eastern Studies, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence relating to monthly stipends that Doris Duke sent to Lillie Holt and Ellen Keller, 1930-1963 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence relating to the purchase of Bonnie jackets by Doris Duke, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Memoranda relating to Doris Duke's excess umbrella liability insurance coverage, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence relating to Joey Castro d/b/a J.C. Recording Company and Atlantic Recording Corporation, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Letter to Redwood Library and Athenaeum, re: Doris Duke's indefinite loan of Julia Ward Howe bust, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Faxes received by Doris Duke, re: maintenance work performed at other estates. Faxes sent to Duke Farms, 1990 (1 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Faxes received by Doris Duke, re: maintenance work performed at other estates. Faxes sent to Duke Farms, 1990 (2 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Memoranda relating to evening gown donation to the Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence and other related materials concerning Prince Modupe D. Paris's business venture, Modupe Foods, Inc., 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to hoax wedding announcement between Doris Duke and Michael Novak, as declared by Novak. File includes newspaper clippings and phony invitation/flyer, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, Dr. Orentreich, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence relating to personal donations from Doris Duke to various institutions, 1959-1971 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence and memoranda, re: personal matters of Doris Duke's. Subjects include travel arrangements, charitable contributions, dancing lessons, etc., 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence and memoranda, regarding personal matters of Doris Duke's, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and memoranda, regarding personal matters of Doris Duke's, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and other materials, regarding personal matters of Doris Duke's, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, membership forms, and other documents relating to personal matters of Doris Duke's, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and memoranda, re: personal matters of Doris Duke's. Materials include Paris retail store invoices, account applications, letters asking for help, and Babies Hospital Board of Women Managers list (DD was a member), 1982-1984 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and notes relating to Doris Duke's purchase of theater tickets, 1969-1975 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Memoranda and related materials concerning personal purchases made by Chandi Heffner and Doris Duke, 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to Doris Duke's assistance to Mr. Donald Rampert with leg braces and shoes, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence and related materials documenting the activities of Paola Riva, a maid at Doris Duke's 3 E. 84th St., PH, and 1 E. 78th St, 1947-1962 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, notes, and related materials concerning Doris Duke's hiring of Whittaker Associates to investigate a robbery at Duke Farms (November 28, 1973) and indictment of Mr. Whittaker for practicing in the State of N.J. without a license, 1973-1978 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence relating to the shipment of food packages to Antonia Ruffini, in Rome, from Doris Duke Rubirosa, 1948-1964 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Memoranda and related materials concerning the purchase of Doris Duke's bras from Saks Fifth Avenue, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and related materials concerning the sale of painting, "Girl Playing a Stringed Instrument," by Sotheby Parke-Bernet, 1976-1979 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Auction catalog pages (photocopies) and related materials (Tiffany swan), 1987, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Memoranda and related materials concerning the silver collection, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence and shipping information of a stained glass window, originally loaned to Duke University and then sent to Shangri La (Turkish Room), 1988 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence relating to Doris Duke's hiring of The Wackenhut Corp. for investigative services. Also included in the file are copies of a legal Complaint, "Doris Duke against Robert Tashjian", 1974 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence and related materials concerning the cost of tickets for The International Antiques Dealers Show, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence relating to a donation of tapestries to The North Carolina State Art Society, 1955–1960, 1970, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Memoranda and lists of furniture, regarding transfer of belongings of Walker Inman, Jr. to South Carolina from N.J. and R.I. and from Georgetown, S.C. to Newport, 1972–1979 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to donations of wine made by Doris Duke to the University of Hawaii, 1977-1978 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence and FAX transmissions relating to the shipment of wine from Walker Inman to Doris Duke at Falcon Lair, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence and copies of correspondence addressed to/from Doris Duke. Subjects mainly include business matters, The Doris Duke Foundation, loans, Independent Charitable Aid, Inc. and the purchase of a B-25J plane (1/6/1948). File also includes some personal letters between Doris Duke and her half brother, Walker Inman Sr. and "Ma" (1947). Also includes letters about legal claims of James Cromwell in N.J., 1944-1952 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, lists of shipments from N.Y. to Paris, notes relating to Doris Duke's 2 apartments in Paris, bank accounts with Morgan Guaranty in Paris, and routine matters with staff at 30 Rockefeller Plaza, 1948-1968 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and related materials concerning personnel, office meetings, and procedures as they pertain to the N.Y. office, 1961-1969 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence from Edwardo Tirella to Pete Cooley while in Paris with Doris Duke (1962). File also includes letters about legal matters in R.I., 1962-1970 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence relating to a variety of issues involving Doris Duke's construction projects, the buying of 60 acres opposite Duke Farms entrance, and Edwardo Tirella's work on designs for Doris Duke, 1963-1968 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to a variety of subjects. Subjects include Edwardo Tirella's death, the use of Rough Point as a backdrop to a TV series, and reports to Doris Duke from Peter Cooley, 1964–1966 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence relating to Allan, Foster, Ingersoll & Weber (PR firm), services to Doris Duke. Topics include fashion shoots in Duke Gardens, the American Indian Project, and charities donated to by the Doris Duke Foundation, 1964-1967 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to Doris Duke's authority on certain items to pay bills, 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Memoranda, miscellaneous, referring to a variety of routine matters, 1971–1988, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and notes, re: variety of personal issues. Topics include burglary of Doris Duke's room at Duke Farms (11/28/1973), the use of firearms by staff, the possible relocation of the DBO from N.Y.C. to N.J., The Duke Endowment, and the Lease and termination of Lease for land in Hillsborough, N.J. to The Animal Medical Center, 1973–1976 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence to Doris Duke from Phillip Alampi of the N.J. Agricultural Society, inquiring about land at Duke Farms for a 4-H Camp and some matters concerning The Animal Medical Center, 1974-1975 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to a variety of issues including Somerset County College land, a petition made against Doris Duke from U.S. Customs, payments for services, etc., 1975-1976 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and related materials concerning largely business matters. Subjects include general inquiries, requests for donations, and invitations to meetings/luncheons, 1975-1977 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and copies of financial forms (credit card applications, travelers cheques, etc.), 1980 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and related materials concerning Sotheby's purchases and Rough Point repairs, 1942-1990 and undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Magazine articles mentioning Doris Duke, 1957 (Ladies Home Journal), 1990 (Connoisseur), and 1992 (Mirabella) (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper clippings about Doris Duke, 1950, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - 6 datebooks, 3 address books, undated, 1981–1985, 1988–1993; 2 address books in Doris Duke's hand (circa 1988–1993) (Oversize-box 9)
  - 11 datebooks; 1971–1980, with the exception of 1973 (Oversize-box 10)
  - Memorial tribute to James B. Duke from the Duke Endowment, 1925 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Phone book, circa 1940s-1960s (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Phone book, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Phone books - business contacts, possibly used at Duke Farms, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Phone book, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous tips for household goods, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Burial plot - M.E. Vroom, 1973-1974 (Box 19, Folder 7)